[Music]
welcome to the busy Center Lounge event
and our session about news in
legislation and localization in busy
Central where my colleagues pred and
arur together with me will try to
explain what is new in area for specific
countries but also in delivering
legislation features available as a
global features and of course do not
forget delocalization process is one of
the most
important agenda for today doesn't look
so complicated we will first explain
some details about legislation scope
then first show some result of the
localization effort continue with
improvements in regulatory features and
we will finish with one new interesting
topic new report setting feature
so let's
start instead of explaining legislation
scope I will explain our legislation
Mission and this is making organizations
compliant with various set for by
government regulation agency by
providing features that automate
regulatory tasks so organizations can
focus on their primary business it
sounds good so what is important being
compliant and try to automate it
whenever it's possible so sometimes
automations come later as first we need
to deliver feature on a basic level on a
time but there are always something we
are thinking about in the first
place uh today we will show in detail
some of our new features as we cannot
show all of them but this is exactly why
we made this list to show in more
details what we have done in this area
you can see for example we are starting
with the forcing digital vouchers e
documents and these features will not be
show in this presentation because you
can find uh additional sessions related
with enforcing digital vouches and with
completely with uh e documents then you
will see you three-party trade automatic
account codes registration numbers new
format in audit files interest
improvements again we will not show NCT
V improvements because this is something
we already deliver in previous series
then some V date improvements again
independent session and so on and so on
you will see a lot of interest things
today but you can just see that we
deliver much more in this
period and except previous list of
features we also deliver new set of
countries this is very important for
extended Market actually these new
countries will be available from
December this year to be accurate we
added to the cloud new 23 countries with
this release from December this year our
Cloud solution will be available on 155
markets around the glob markets I think
on countries or
regions let's look in details what are
we planning and what we did in previous
period related with the global features
in the
localization uh our localization and the
localization strategy is based on four
pillars first pillar is to enrich our
core base application and this is
something many of our teams are working
on every day I explain it in a detail
for a
minute then everything what cannot be
used as a global feature should be
delivered as extension as the local app
this local app can be for one country
this is only for one market or maybe for
two or three countries if this is some
Regional but again we are treating this
as a local app so idea is to have one
Bas app globally one Bas app for all
countries this is idea but this is as we
said strategy idea is strategy and
probably very long process but we are
going this
direction of course in a par idea is to
bring bring business Central Cloud to
all markets where we see traction and as
I just said we are on new 23 countries
with this wave this is a huge effort and
last but not least everything what we
are doing now is in the first place
optimized for accessibility so you can
easily extend functionality if it's not
100% fit with your requirements for
example we cannot deliver everything to
be fit with all your needs and what we
need to do we need to look to make as
simplify UI possible uh to be 100% fit
with 80 or 90% of markets if in a few uh
countries something more is required we
want to create this extendable so you
can easily extend this feature to be
100% fit on your market and this is not
only with markets connected with Market
this is almost connected with specific
Industries because some specific
industry will need a bit more so you can
easily extend all our features this is
Trend what we are doing and we are
looking in this in the first
place if we look at how we can enrich
the W1 base app and already do these
features can basically come from two
sources we have features that exist in
different flavors in various count that
we can rethink and refactor with the
global mindset and put into W1 Bas app
not only W1 Bap you can see in this
pyramid there is BAS app but there
global apps as well one of the biggest
examples from previous relas not this
but previous relas wasable V8 is a huge
effort it was in three different
countries different architecture with
Belgium uh Norway and Italy and now we
delocalize completely functionality and
deliver to this as a W1 uh Bas W1
feature but en reaching the Bas app can
also be with new features we don't
already have over time doing this will
allow us to scrape off layers of
localization ultimately ending up with a
smaller localization Footprints now I
will not talk about details uh what is
new in uh in reaching uh Bas app from
this perspective because you can see in
application legislation uh Parts on bu
launch event many many really good new
features but as we talk only about this
new release the best examples of the
localization effort and moving these
existing uh flavors to Bay app or some
of global apps are EU three-party trade
and account automatic account codes now
my colleague P will explain more about
about uh these two efforts and before
these two efforts he will first explain
completely the localization C
localization process and now show more
about these new these two new features
pred thank you
Alexander one of the most important
pillars of localization strategy as
mentioned before is process of
modelization and open sourcing local
functionalities so-call delocalization
process so let's say take a look on the
localization status right now prior to
this release we had three countries
completely developed on on top of common
layer socalled W1 with this release we
will have one more country Sweden where
we completely removed the Swedish local
functionalities into app the idea is to
have uh other countries delocalized um
uh also and the next one going to be
Iceland the global plan is to be a
little bit more aggressive on the on
that way so that we can achieve that
goal in the near
future let's now take a look on the
timeline to get Swedish localization
completely removed this is also
important to understand because all
other of functionalities that's going to
be deprecated going to to follow this
plan we started process of
delocalization with version 22 and then
with version 23 which is going to be
released on on 1st of October all this
the local specific Swedish code will be
marked with tag obsolete pending that
will actually mean that in next three
releases users will be able to use this
functionalities uh all functionalities
on the same way but this is also signal
that uh from in version 26 uh all the
this new functionalities should be
enabled after that old Cod will be
tagged with obsolete removed tag and and
uh will be accessible only to the
upgrade
code finally with version 29 a whole
specific Swedish code will be deleted
from the Bas app with the exception of
tables and then in version 30 all local
tables with data will be completely
removed it is important to notice that a
process of deleting code is not
following the same um same pattern as
deleting tables
as we are deleting tables in the every
fifth
release now let's take a look on those
two apps that we got from uh from
Swedish de localization process so the
first one is European Union third party
trade app uh for purchase
transactions this uh app should help
customers that are receiving uh purchase
invoice from customer in one country one
EU country and the product are sent to
different European country or region
without enter in the country of
residence in some European countries in
order to stay comply it is necessary to
report such transactions to the V
reports to to actually uh be aligned
with the V
requirements now with business Central
it is possible to do that so let's take
a look how that can um how that can be
done by creating purchase transaction
now it's also possible to Define that
transaction is actually EU three-party
trade transaction as you can see on the
in this example of the purchase invoice
document going to the after posting such
a document user will be able to navigate
to the vat
statement and for demonstrational
purposes I added the line which will
actually include only u3 part trade uh
purchase transactions there are also
other options to include all
transactions or or to exclude eu3 party
trade uh transactions after running this
report user will be able to get filter
filter transactions in one of the lines
so so that it will be so they will be
able to report this to
government the other app that uh we
prepared uh here is um is automatic
account code app uh one can use
customized posting group to automate
recurring transactions in journals sales
or purchase
documents these posting groups can be
used through business cental to trigger
automatic posting and allocation across
different accounts or
Dimensions uh when this can be handy so
for example when posting total salary
expenses at the end of the month you can
use automatic account codes to assign
percentage of the total salary to
automatically post as overhead expenses
let's take a look how that looks
within the product the first point is
navigating to automatic account groups
page where user can Define automatic
account group um and in this example you
can see the metric of how the alloc
allocation will be applied as mentioned
before Department code and project code
can also be defined from this point
usage of automatic account C codes is
pretty simple I will use sales invoice
as an example but can be also used from
the journal lines now we're getting to
the to the sales document to the sales
line um now I can
Define my automatic account
code and after posting results should be
the set of GL entries which are actually
created based on the previously defined
metrix as you can
see so those two functionalities are
going to be available in other European
countries with that I will pass to arur
who will continue presentation or other
features that we delivered with this
release thank you
pck uh while the VAR registration number
is um required during the registration
in certain countries in other countries
uh there is additional registration
required by authorities and that leads
us to add the additional field that is
called registration number this
registration number number field uh is
added in multiple places across
application company information customer
vendor and contact cards and the
important part is that when you add this
field uh to the contact card it will be
copied to the customer or vendor card
just like other
fields audit File Expert audit File
Expert is a functionality that provides
an interface for extension to expert
accounting and tax data it allows you to
work with different formats like
Norwegian sft Swedish s and French
Fe for this functionality it's possible
to schedule execution to out of work
hours it is also possible to run the
parallel processing for better
performance and provides a various of
options like splitting the data by
months by date experting to the Z
archive or experting with additional
information let's talk a little bit more
about the file the important part of
this functionality is that it provides
you uh uh an ability to define the data
to expert you can export Master data you
can export documents and you can export
Ledger entries so at every single point
you can Define what kind of data you
want to
export the second second part is GL
account mapping uh authorities required
to map your chart accounts to the
standard accounts uh uh when you expert
the data and audit File Expert extension
provides you the possibility to do
this and last but not least the
architecture of that solution the AUD
File Expert extension uh needs to be
extended by the specific form expansion
so audit F expert extension provides you
the following things this is GL account
mapping interface for data source
interface for data check handling of
audit file document scheduling exec
ution and parallel processing while the
specific form expansions implements the
data sources and Define what exactly you
want to expert and implements the data
check to check what data needs to be
verified before expert and Audi file
format
itself okay thank you Arthur um let's
see uh what we have more about
regulatory features let's see what is
new in
interet uh before I continue with this
topic you will see here uh use drop
shipment for triangular interest trade
and first what is the triangle trade at
all triangle trade involves trade
between companies located in three
countries or regions where Goods bypass
the report in company's country as our
country for example in bus Central you
can use draw Shi and the standard
feature to handle triangle trade but for
interat to use drop shipment you must
turn on include drop shipment tole in
interest report seta page now when you
enable this feature this feature allow
uh allows for scenarios where a company
ordered goods from one EU country and
drop ships to Goods uh drop ships Goods
directly to another your country without
importing this good into its own country
classic bypassing a drop shipment in
such case the interet report will
exclude all these transactions because
the goods are directly delivered between
two other European Union countries
without entering uh into our country the
calculation is based on the following
information from item Ledger entries
entries are marked as a drop shipment
and Country region code in item ler ENT
is different than country region code on
the company information
page okay that's not all
um just not forget interat is now
localized for Czech Republic as well so
all countries with new release now will
use new inter module
globally okay this feat about um draw
shipment trade on the first s is small
but definely important Improvement and
um it proved that we are dedicated to
continue Improvement for existing
feature not only for interet but for
inter for other features we are creating
that means they will not stop when we
deliver this feature we continue to
improve this uh in the next
period okay uh now
finally new report settings uh feature
so PR can you continue with your
presentation thank you
Alexander with the wave 2023 we are also
introducing improvements in report
formatting before introducing this
change it was not possible to change the
formatting in reports from the
application and the reports would always
be formatted as per my settings page in
cases when language in report has been
set to different language than the one
that it is defined in my settings for
for example in customer vendor card the
only way to change format in that report
would be to change the format in my
settings this was of course TDS and
error error PR process so we are trying
to introduce the support for original
format on the same way how that was
implemented for the
language this L shows how format can be
defined for particular reports by
priority so the latest change will
support user to Define both language and
format on the request page of the
report we have also introduced support
for setting up properformance from mail
code on the same way how it was done for
the language finally using the same
pattern it is possible to define
specific format for specific customer or
vendor at the end if none of of of above
was changed language and formats from my
settings will be used for printing the
report let's now take a look how it
looks like on different pages so this is
the newly introduced property on the
request page where now within Advanced
app it is now possible to define format
region and language for that
report the new think is also support for
defining format region directly from the
AL code so that current report object
now has property called format region
third option is to define the language
and format region for specific customer
so this is the same pattern that we use
for language now it is also possible to
print reports for particular customer or
vendor um by definition within the
vendor or customer card as mentioned
before if if none of above was
changed uh the fback mechanism will use
region and language from my settings to
print the
report we are hoping that with this
feature we will provides more
flexibility for the users working on the
report at the same time non-breaking
current
experience with that I'll pass back to
Alexander okay thank you pred for such a
good presentation about new features in
uh report settings this is definitely
really good feature uh what you can see
and before we finally close this session
I would like um to call you to to watch
all busy Central lunch event sessions
but these three are really important if
you are uh if you already watch this
session because there are continuation
of that and really connected with this
these features in these sessions we just
show this is Introduction in electronic
invoicing or electronic documents then
what's new about V dat is a really
important Improvement
uh we will explain much more in details
what is new and to clarify some other uh
I say issues and using of enforcing
digital vowers again really important
regulatory feature uh we deliver in this
release yes um I would like to invite
you also to uh to join one of these um
groups or communities if you cannot
remember all of them try not to forget
AK Ms BC all where you can find all our
resources on one
page okay thank you for watching uh this
session and please watch other sessions
for this lunch event thank
you